你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院高级开发模块的另一个视频
welcome to another video in Advanced Exploitation Module of pwn College
今天我们要讲的是
today we're going to be talking about
逃离seccomp
escaping seccomp
如果你还记得的话
if you recall
Seccomp是一种内核沙盒技术
seccomp is a kernel sandboxing technique
它会限制你能运行的系统调用的类型
that limits the types of system calls you can run
并限制系统调用的参数
and limits the arguments to these syscalls
基本上它可以让你创建安全的沙盒
and basically it lets you create secure sandboxes
如果你正确地创建了seccomp沙盒
if you create a seccomp sandbox properly
正如我在沙盒模块中提到的那样
as I mentioned in the sandboxing module
它可以是无法逃脱的
it can be impossible to break out of
但你还能用一些系统调用与内核模块交互
except for you can still interact in all of these modules with certain system calls
如果你触发了内核中的漏洞
and if you trigger vulnerabilities in the kernel
你就可以逃离seccomp沙盒
you can escape the seccomp sandbox
正如我在那个模块中提到的
as I mentioned in that module
有很多沙盒可以逃脱
there's some a good amount of sandbox escapes from
例如Chrome沙盒，其中使用seccomp
for example the Chrome sandbox which uses among other things seccomp
在这个Git仓库中讨论了它
that are discussed at this Git repository
但在沙盒模块时
but I at the time doing the sandboxing module
我说过，把它留到内核漏洞利用模块
I said just hold on for the kernel exploitation module
当时我们没讲这么深
we never made it that far in kernel exploitation
因为我们要缩短那个模块
because we had to just shorten that module
但现在我们已经走到了这一步了
but now we are making it that far
那么，为什么可以使用内核漏洞来逃离seccomp呢
so why can you escape seccomp using kernel vulnerabilities
如果你还记得的话
well if you recall
内核是整个系统的尽头
the kernel is the kind of end all of the system
内核以极高特权运行
the kernel runs with extreme privileges
内核会记录，例如seccomp
and the kernel keeps track of for example seccomp
Seccomp是在内核内部实现的
seccomp is implemented inside the kernel
它的实现方式非常类似内核模块
and it's implemented in a very similar way
或者说，和内核模块在相似的级别上
or on a similar level as kernel modules are in general
所以如果你有一个有漏洞的内核模块
so if you have a kernel module that has a vulnerability
它对seccomp元数据，有与seccomp本身相同的访问权限
that vulnerability has equal access to the seccomp metadata that seccomp itself does
我们开始深入吧
let's dig in
这会很疯狂的
this is gonna get kind of wild
前面我们看到了Linux内核中的cred结构
so we have previously seen the cred struct in the Linux kernel
我们使用这个cred结构
we use this cred struct
用commit_creds和prepare_kernel_creds
with set creds and prepare_kernel_creds
获取root权限
to achieve root access
在内核漏洞利用模块中
in the kernel exploitation module
cred结构体是task_struct的成员
the cred struct is a member of the task_struct
task_struct中还有其他数据
and the task_struct has other data in it as well
在task_struct中有个内联结构体
it has inlined inside the task_struct a
算是子结构体，thread_info
kind of substructure of thread_info
在thread_info中
and in that thread_info
有个flags变量
there are among other things a flags variable
flags包含很多比特位
and flags holds a bunch of bits
这些位
and these bits
它是一个位域
it's a bitfield
这些比特编码了一堆选项
these bits encode a bunch of options
其中包括一个名为TIF_SECCOMP的选项
including an option called TIF_SECCOMP
我记得是flags中的第8位
I think it is bit 8 in the flag struct
它所做的当然是启用seccomp
and what it does of course is enable seccomp
如果你对这个很感兴趣
if you are very interested in this
对它在Linux内核中是如何工作的感兴趣
in terms of how these things work deep down inside in the linux kernel
那我强烈推荐这个叫做bootlin的网站
highly recommend this site called bootlin
你可以在里面浏览不同版本的Linux内核源码
where you can crawl around the Linux kernel source code of different versions etc
可以点击函数名跳转
click through it
非常好用
it's super nice
你可以自己找到所有这些
and you can track down all of this on your own
总之，重点是
anyways the point is
在task_struct的thread_info子结构中
in the thread_info substructure of the task_struct
有一个flags变量保存TIF_SECCOMP
there is a flags variable that holds TIF_SECCOMP
TIF_SECCOMP是如何使用的
how is TIF_SECCOMP used
我们要看一下seccomp是如何在内核中实现的
we have to kind of back up and look at how seccomp is implemented in the kernel
在Linux内核的系统调用处理程序中
at one point in the syscall handler in the Linux kernel
有一处调用了secure_computing函数
there is a call to the secure_computing function
secure_computing函数是
the secure_computing function again is a
在Linux内核中用来实现seccomp的
what is used to implement seccomp in the Linux kernel
在系统调用的入口点
so in the syscall entry point
我们会调用secure_computing
we call secure_computing
检查是否设置了TIF_SECCOMP标志
which checks whether or not the TIF_SECCOMP flag is set
如果设置了
and if it is
就调用__secure_computing
calls into __secure_computing
它会弄清楚用户设置了哪些seccomp结构
which figures out what seccomp structure has been set
比如设置了哪些seccomp选项
like what the seccomp options are
然后执行seccomp过滤器
and then executes the seccomp filter
这就是seccomp在内核中的实现方式
this is how seccomp is implemented in the kernel
这一切都取决于这个seccomp标志
and it all hinges on this seccomp flag
就是thread_info结构体里的标志
which is a flag on the thread_info struct
那么，结论是什么呢
so what's the takeaway
结论是，我们可以逃离seccomp
the takeaway is that we can escape seccomp
我们可以关闭当前线程的seccomp
we can disable seccomp for our current thread
通过task_struct
by taking the task_struct
获取thread_info.flags的偏移量
getting the offset of thread_info.flags and
叫什么来着
what's it called
翻转TIF_SECCOMP位
flipping the TIF_SECCOMP bit
我展示一下，实际C代码中，这是什么样子的
let me show you what that will look like in actual C code
首先是比特位翻转的样子
first what this bitflip actually looks like
我们想要
so we actually want to of course
这是一个比特域
this is a bit field
TIF_SECCOMP是索引
TIF_SECCOMP is the index
我记得是8
I think it's 8
但它显然会根据内核版本的不同而不同
but it obviously can change kernel versions to kernel version
我们有8位
we have 8 bit
第8位
a number it's bit number 8
我们将1
and we take a one bit
左移8个比特
we shift it to the left by 8
再取个反
we invert it
于是我们创建一个字段，每个位都是1，除了右起第8位
so we create a field where every bit is one except for the 8th bit from the right
然后我们把它和flags按位与
and then we and it with the flags
这样就关闭了一个标志位
thus disabling a single flag
一些基础知识
couple of basics
怎么找到flags的地址
how do we get to the address of these flags
我们很幸运
well we're in luck
因为相比其他信息，当前task_struct会频繁使用
because the current task_struct is used so frequently among some other information
所以内核一直把GS段寄存器指向当前task_struct
that the kernel always points the segment register GS to the current task_struct
这是寄存器，你可以
this is a register that you can
它类似于FS寄存器
that is analogous to the FS register
后者你经常在金丝雀的比较中看到
that you often see in the comparisons of canaries
这样用户空间程序才有一个比较项
so the user space program has a reference to among other things
就是fs寄存器中的金丝雀值
the canary from the FS register
如果你反汇编一个被金丝雀保护的程序
if you disassemble something that's protected by Canary
你可以看到是如何访问fs的
you can see how that access works
GS也是一样的
GS is the same
在linux内核中，它用于访问当前的task_struct
in the Linus kernel it is used for an access to the current task_struct
在内核开发中
and in kernel development
其实有一个很简单的简写
there's actually a really easy shorthand for this
叫current
called current
它返回当前的task_struct
that just returns the current task_struct
关闭thread_info.flags中TIF_SECCOMP标志的方法是
so the plan to disable the TIF_SECCOMP flag from the thread_info flags is
通过GS Register获取该结构的访问权限
get the access to this structure via the GS Register
清零这个标志位
clear the flag
完成
done
这里需要注意的是，这个进程的子进程
caveat here is that the children of this process
此进程将不再被seccomp保护
this process will no longer be seccomped
但它的子进程仍受到seccomp保护
but its children will still be seccomped
继承的seccomp信息存储在别处
that information inherited seccomp rules and stuff are stored elsewhere
让我们在实践中看看这一点
let's take a look at this in practice
我扩展了pwnkernel仓库中的make_root.ko或make_root.c，
so I extended make_root.ko or make_root.c rather in the pwnkernel repository
提醒一下
so as a reminder
Pwnkernel在
pwnkernel is at
github.com/pwncollege/pwnkernel
在src下面
here under src
make_root.c
有很多
there's a lot of
有几个不同的内核模块
there are several different kernel modules
它们会显示内核的不同功能
that will show different functionalities in the kernel
你可以构建内核
you can build the kernel
执行build.sh
you will build.sh
用launch启动它
launch it with launch and
我不小心给你看错了东西
I accidentally showed you the wrong thing
现在我们开始吧
but here we go
github.com/pwncollege/pwnkernel
我展示一下正确的窗口
let me show the right window
好了
boom
在pwnkernel中
so in pwnkernel
我们有一个名为make_root的模块
we have a module called make_root
make_root有一个ioctl处理程序
and make_root has an ioctl handler
如果发送ioctl参数13371337
if you send an ioctl parameter 13371337
它会给你root权限
it'll give you root access
正如我们在内核漏洞利用模块中看到的那样
as we saw in the kernel exploitation module
如果发送参数31337
if you send a parameter of 31337
它会为你逃脱seccomp
it'll escape seccomp for you
这是代码
and this is the code
这个_TIF_SECCOMP实际上是一个宏的简写
this _TIF_SECCOMP is actually a shorthand for a macro
它将1左移，不带下划线的TIF_SECCOMP次
that does one shifted to the left by TIF_SECCOMP without the underscore
和ppt上的是一回事
so it's the same thing
这将清除seccomp标志
and this will clear the seccomp flag
我们演示一下逃出这个沙盒
so let's demonstrate this by breaking out of this sandbox
我写了一个非常有效的沙盒
I wrote a sandbox that is actually very effective
我们有一个
we have a
它将ruid、euid和saved uid设置为1234
it sets the real effective and saved user ID to 1234
没法从中逃脱
no escape from that
然后它创建了一个严格的seccomp
and then it creates a strict seccomp
它只允许你用ioctl读写
that only allows you ioctl read and write
默认情况下，其它系统调用都返回-1337
by default it'll return -1337 from every other system call
这样为了展示逃脱效果
that's to demonstrate this breakout
方便我写日志之类的
so that I can log and stuff
玩玩沙盒
poke at the sandbox
很多沙盒，如果你违反规则，就直接杀死你的进程
of course many sandboxes will just kill your process if you violated
这个更好
this one is nicer
然后我们演示一下，这个会返回-1337
then we're going to show that this will return -1337
这行不通
this will not work
不会调用getuid
will not call getuid
因为系统调用被拦截了
because that syscall is blocked
但当我们针对文件描述符3，执行ioctl时
but then when we do this ioctl on file descriptor 3
幸运的是，我们之前打开过它
which luckily we opened before
用来进入
jumping into the
什么来着
what's it called
沙盒
the sandbox
然后执行ioctl 31337
and we do the ioctl 31337
我们将逃离沙盒
we will have escaped the sandbox
酷
cool
我们来看看
so let's take a look
这些实际上都是不必要的
all of this is actually not necessary
我们开始吧
let's do this
与其
and rather than
硬编码
hard coding it
不如我们把这个传进去
we'll pass this in
这就是我们的attack
so we have our attack
我们的沙盒和进攻程序
our sandbox and our attack
我们来编译一下
let's compile this
还记得
remember
在pwnkernel内部使用
for use inside pwnkernel
因为在用户空间中没有库
because there are no libraries in there in user space
你要编译静态代码
you probably want to compile static
我们启动
let's launch
安装这个make_root模块
let's uh install this make_root module
然后我们启动/home/ctf/
and then we just launch /home/ctf/
和
and
找到我们的沙盒
find our sandbox
好的
boom
它失败了
it failed
为什么失败了
why did it fail
我暂停一下，看看发生了什么
let me pause it and I'll figure out what's going on
我之前刚测试过，是有效的
I just tested this and it worked
我一定是弄乱了什么东西
but I must have broken something
好的，我回来了
all right I'm back
明显，最初的沙盒逃逸是有效的
obviously the original sandbox escape worked
因为某些原因，我在和你谈话的时候删掉了这部分
and for some reason I deleted this part when talking to you
这对获取root权限很关键
which is critical to get root privileges
没有它我就打不开flag
and without which I can't open the flag
因为我会降到1234的权限
because of course I drop privileges to 1234
这里沙盒逃逸有两步
so we have a two step sandbox escape here
沙盒有两个部分
there are two parts of the sandbox
seccomp这部分
the seccomp
和降低用户权限到1234这部分
and the user UID drop  the privilege drop
所以首先我们要逃出沙盒
so first we break out of the sandbox
然后我们
and then we break out of the
然后我们提升我们的特权
and then we elevate our privileges
我们可以看到
and we can see
这个会失败
that this here is going to fail
这个getuid调用
this call to getuid
因为它不在seccomp过滤器中
because it's not included in the seccomp filter
它将返回错误码-1337
it'll return on error 1337
这里的调用会成功
and then this call right here will succeed
因为我们已经关闭了seccomp过滤器
because we have disabled the seccomp filter
如果我们运行这个
if we run this
哦，我运行了
oh I ran it earlier
如果我们运行这个
if we run this
我们让make_root.ko打日志输出了
we get make_root.ko logging
以前的flags是多少
what the flags were before
之后的flags是多少
what the flags were after
这是从0开始的第8位（输出的是0x100）
so this is the 8th bit if 0 indexed of course
设置了TIF_SECCOMP
TIF_SECCOMP is set
没设TIF_SECCOMP
TIF_SECCOMP is not set
我们开始吧
and here we go
在逃离前
we said before breaking out
getuid返回-1337
our getuid was negative 1337
逃离后
then we broke out
当然这是
of course this is
有输出缓冲
this is all buffered
它会立即输出
this gets output immediately
所以输出结果应该是交叉的，但没有
so this should be interlieved but it's not
在我们逃出沙盒之前
before we broke out the sandbox
getUID返回-1337
our getUID was negative 1337
然后我们逃离
then we broke out
然后getuid输出1234
then was 1234
然后我们提权
then we elevated privileges
获取flag
and then we got the flag
那么我们怎么弄清楚
so how do we actually figure out
它的汇编指令
what the assembly of this is
正如我们在内核模块中发现的那样
as we found out in the kernel module
反汇编这个很烦
disassembling these things is kind of annoying
当然，你可以在它执行的时候，用gdb查看
of course you can always check it out in GDB as it executes
这是device_ioctl的地址
so here's the device ioctl
你可以
you can
gdb
GDB
附加上
attach
我们设置断点了吗
did we does it set the break point
好的，继续
yes okay continue
运行沙盒
run the sandbox
现在我们在断点
now we are in the break point
然后我们
and we go
执行si
step instruction
提醒一下
as a reminder
有时在某些版本的GDB上
sometimes on certain versions of GDB
ni不起作用
next instruction doesn't actually work
但你可以si进入一个函数
but you can step into a function
然后输入finish完成它
and then type finish to finish it
好了
here we go
我们在比较13371337
we're comparing 13371337
这是提权的那段代码
that's the root privilege elevation
这段代码
this guy
这还不是当前沙盒逃逸要做的
this is not what we're currently doing in the sandbox attack
我们跳过这个
so we skip that
现在我们和31337进行比较
now we're comparing against 31337
这就是我们要做的
that is what we're doing
我们进入
we go there
我们要打印出：我们正在逃离沙盒
so we're gonna printk that we're escaping the sandbox
你可以在这里看到
you can see that here
好吧
OK
这里我们要打印
and here we're gonna print
之前的标记位
the flags before
这里写着“之前的标志位”
Ops this says flags before
这里写着“之后的标志位”
and this says flags after
不对，这里写的是“之后的标志位”
no this says flags after
你得看习惯内核的高内存地址
you'll have to get used to seeing the kernel high memory addresses again
那么标志位在哪里呢
so where are flags
标志位在这里
of course our flags go here
这是
this is
这个放到了要传给printk的rdi寄存器
this gets put to RDI into printk
标志位在RSI
our flags are in RSI
标志位从RBX读取到RSI
and our flags are read from RBX into RSI
RBX在这里
and RBX is right here
这个GS偏移量
that GS offset
这是一个真的指令
this is an actual instruction
它用GS段寄存器
that takes the GS segment register
就是一个指向内存某处的寄存器
just a register that points indexes somewhere into memory
从该处偏移0x15d00
and indexes 0x15d00 off of that
那就是标志位的位置
and that's where the flags are
然后
and then of course
在这里，它清除了位于第8位的TIF_SECCOMP
here is where it clears out the 8th bit of the flags
非常酷
very cool
这就是逃离沙盒的方法
so that is how you escape a sandbox
我们看到的这种形式是可能的
of course this is all possible in the form that we saw
这就是通过内核漏洞逃离seccomp沙盒的方法
this is how you escape seccomp sandbox through a kernel vulnerability
显然，内核模块不会故意关闭seccomp过滤器
obviously kernel modules aren't going to disable your seccomp filter purposely
肯定是由于某种疯狂的错误
it'll be through some sort of crazy mistake
才让你关
that allows you to
例如
for example
如果你利用一个内核代码执行
if you code execution a kernel
然后像这样做
and do something like this
基本上在内核中
basically in the kernel
一旦你进入内核，并执行代码
once you're in there and executing code
就游戏结束了
it's really game over
希望你们已经看到了
and hopefully you have seen that already
你还会看到更多关于关闭seccomp的例子
but you'll see it even more with this seccomp disabling